Register of the Fellowship of Reconciliation Records, 1942-1946.
Hoover Institution Archives
Fellowship of Reconciliation Records,
1942-1946.
XX105
Fellowship of Reconciliation (U.S.)
20 manuscript boxes (8.3 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Correspondence, reports, and memoranda, relating to pacifist activities and conscientious objectors in the United States during World War II.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Access Points
Conscientious objectors--United States.; Pacifism.; Peace.; World War, 1939-1945.; World War, 1939-1945--Conscientious objectors.; World War, 1939-1945--United States.; United States.
Container List
- Container List
  - a. Legal service to conscientious objectors. (Box 1.)
  - b. National Committee on Conscientious Objectors (NCCO) - minutes, correspondence and memos.
  - c. National Service Board for Religious Objectors (NSBRO) - reports, memoranda, forms, etc.
  - d. Philadelphia Council for Conscientious Objectors - correspondence.
  - e. Metropolitan Board for Conscientious Objectors, N.Y. - correspondence, reports, memoranda, forms, etc.
  - f. Miscellaneous community boards to counsel conscientious objectors.
  - a. American Friends Service Committee - correspondence, reports, memoranda. (Box 2.)
  - b. Amnesty - miscellaneous materials printed in N.Y. Committee for Amnesty for all Objectors to War and Conscription.
  - c. Anti-war organizations - correspondence, reports, memoranda, etc.
  - d. Army cases dealing with conscientious objectors - correspondence, memoranda, reports, forms, etc.
  - e. Baptist Church contacts.
  - f. Brethren Service Committee.
  - Bulletins concerning various organizations of conscientious objectors. (Box 3.)
  - a. Civil Public Service (CPS) Camp Papers - bulletins, reports, and pamphlets. (Box 4.)
  - b. Congressional Record - excerpts.
  - c. Fellowship of Reconciliation - bulletins, minutes, etc.
  - d. "Grapevine" prison news exchange. Cleveland, Ohio.
  - e. National Legislation of Interest to Religious Groups - bulletins.
  - f. "Michigan Reporter for Conscientious Objectors." October, December, 1944.
  - g. Miscellaneous newsletters pertaining to conscientious objectors.
  - h. "News Notes" - printed by the Northern California Service Board, Berkeley, California - scattered issues.
  - i. "Open Forum" - printed by the American Civil Liberties Union. ca. 1944-46.
  - j. "Pacific Citizen." July 8, 1944
  - a. Committee on Demobilization (COD) Interviews - Sacramento, California and vicinity. (Box 5.)
  - b. Same - San Jose, California and vicinity.
  - c. Same - San Francisco, California and vicinity.
  - d. COD - social work.
  - e. Same - cooperatives.
  - f. Same - correspondence.
  - g. Same - demobilization work.
  - h. Civil Service Bulletins (California).
  - i. Christian Church contacts.
  - j. Miscellaneous church material.
  - k. Churches (non-pacifist) - official statements of support of conscientious objectors.
  - l. Same - local and national contacts through service board.
  - m. Same - contacts with the California Methodist Church.
  - n. Civilian Defense.
  - o. Civilian Public Service camps - camp relations.
  - p. Same - conferences.
  - q. Same - detached (Bubonic plague).
  - a. Same - Camp #21, 31, 35, 37, 43, 51, 56, 59, 60, 76, 107, 134, 148. (Box 6.)
  - b. Same - general matters.
  - c. Same - government camp.
  - d. Civilian Public Service finances.
  - a. Civilian Public Service - miscellaneous printed materials. (Box 7.)
  - b. Same - "Releases" and "Walkouts" and miscellaneous data.
  - c. Civilian bonds.
  - d. Committee for Non-violent Revolution.
  - e. Friends for Civilian Public Service materials.
  - f. Congregational Church contacts.
  - g. Civilian Public Service - miscellaneous correspondence.
  - h. Same - correspondence with French, Mead, and Jacob.
  - i. Civilian Public Service - correspondence - A-F.
  - a. Same - G-Z. (Box 8.)
  - b. Same - out of state, A-Z.
  - c. Same - California, A-Z.
  - d. Job opportunities.
  - e. Minutes of meetings of couselors to conscientious objectors.
  - a. "The Reporter." July 1942-June 1946. (Box 9.)
  - b. Demobilization - reports on committee meetings.
  - c. Same - research bulletins of the National Service Board.
  - d. Same - Interagency Demobilization of Committee bulletins. January-June 1946.
  - e. Deposits - records of financial deposits, 1944.
  - f. Episcopalian Church contacts.
  - g. Fellowship of Reconciliation - miscellaneous pamphlets, booklets, and leaflets.
  - h. Financial efforts on behalf of Civilian Public Service - statistical information.
  - i. Same - special routing of contributions.
  - j. Same - stamps and contributions.
  - k. Same - records of financial statements.
  - a. Financial help - miscellaneous materials. (Box 10.)
  - b. Financial charts.
  - c. Furlough jobs.
  - d. Individual draft cases - A-D.
  - e. Same - E-H.
  - f. Same - biographical files of conscientious objectors - A.
  - Same - B-C. (Box 11.)
  - Same - D-F. (Box 12.)
  - Same - G-L. (Box 13.)
  - Same - M-Q. (Box 14.)
  - Same - R-V. (Box 15.)
  - a. Same - W-Z. (Box 16.)
  - b. Interagency Demobilization Committees - job bulletins.
  - c. Interpretation Committee Reports.
  - d. Job information.
  - e. Letters pertaining to financial matters.
  - f. Loan Fund materials.
  - g. Lutheran Church contacts.
  - h. Men coming to N. California.
  - i. Mental Hospitals.
  - j. Methodist Church contacts.
  - k. Miscellaneous printed material.
  - l. Mutual Aid Fund.
  - m. National Service Board Communications.
  - a. Northern California Service Board - financial approaches. (Box 17.)
  - b. Same - financial expenses and accounts.
  - c. Same - employment problems.
  - d. Same - associate volunteer counselors.
  - e. Same - publications (mimeographed).
  - f. Same - draft survey.
  - g. Same - volunteer workers.
  - h. Same - general information.
  - i. Same - statistics.
  - a. Same - Organization #1 (1942). (Box 18.)
  - b. Same - Organization #2 (1943).
  - c. Same - mailing lists.
  - d. Same - news notes.
  - e. Same - IA objectors and weapons.
  - f. Same - Board of Directors.
  - g. Northern California - projected work.
  - h. Pacifism - miscellaneous material.
  - i. Pamphlet materials.
  - j. Parolees.
  - a. Peace Strategy Board. (Box 19.)
  - b. Personnel - secretaries.
  - c. Presbyterian Church contacts.
  - d. Prison cases.
  - e. Probation cases.
  - f. Property information - north of San Francisco, California.
  - g. Service Board - minutes.
  - a. Same - correspondence. (Box 20.)
  - b. Unitarian Church contacts.
  - c. "Washington Merry-go-Round."
  - d. Washington - Oregon contacts.
  - e. Women's International League for Peace and Freedom.
  - f. Working file - revised manual.
  - g. World Peace Newsletters. 1944-45.
  - h. World Organization for Peace - miscellaneous material.